Well, it happened in
the night of Friday and Saturday.
I woke up by the sound
of breaking glass
in my house,
in my bedroom.
I suddenly
realized that
there was a heat,
an enormous
heat in my room.
At the beginning, I thought that my son had put up the
temperature in the house.
Then I realized that there was a fire downstairs.
I immediately got up, but I realized that I couldn't get
out of my bedroom.
The road, way to the stairs, was blocked because of the
heat. I jumped to the floor because there is a small part
of oxygen on the floor, and I started crawling in the dark
smoke looking for the window.
I couldn't find my window.
It's my own bedroom, but I couldn't find my own window.
I panicked a little bit.
There was so much heat.
I found my window, and I realized that I should be very
careful in opening the window.
Because when oxygen enters and there's such a heat and
there might be an explosion.
So little by little, I opened that window.
So I got out in my underwear with no shoes.
I got on the roof of my house.
Luckily, I have a ladder on the roof and so I could escape
from the roof to my garden.
I ran to the street to alert the neighbors because I didn't
have a phone with me.
Because I realized also that as long as I cannot alert the
rescue service of the fire brigade,
then I would be on my own.
Luckily for me, they immediately responded.
I went back because my son was still in the house,
I thought. I knocked on his window,
but there was no reaction.
Then I realized I had to put out a fire myself,
which I did. But then even by putting out a fire,
it was too hot to enter.
And there was all. Everywhere was glass.
Broken glass. With my bare foot,
I couldn't enter.
So I decided to break in.
In the glass of his bedroom.
The window. When I saw the smoke and I felt the heat and I
saw that his bed was empty.
And then I panicked immediately because I thought he ran
away in the wrong direction, and that I would discover him
somewhere on the floor, dead.
But then I realized that the day before,
I dropped him off at the Boy Scout weekend,
so I was extremely happy.
It's only afterwards that I realized what was the cause of
the fire, and it was a battery that was charging during the
night and that battery exploded during the night.
So that explosion has set fire everywhere in my house.
So let's say that that everything in in a circle of 15m
around that battery melted, was burned down.
A lot of heat, which is typical for the battery explosion.
The medics, they took care of me.
They brought me to the hospital.
They examined me.
I had some smoke inhalation, but luckily,
me, it was quite all right.
Trauma. This is an experience that is
quite hard, even for me.
I'm a trained journalist.
I've been in, in, in, in, in Africa in very difficult and
dangerous situations.
But this, this happened in my,
my own house, where in fact I'm very familiar with the
house, especially there.
It's it's like an an attack on your,
your personal on your life, but also intimacy.
That's a, that's a rough one.
Well, in my house we have several smoke alarms.
I didn't hear them.
And the reason why is that after the fire,
we examined the place and we found the smoke alarms.
They were all melted. As a precaution for the future.
I will install in my house smoke alarms.
But that are in connection with each other.
That even if there is a fire far away from your bedroom
within your house or in your your cellar or whatever,
that all the smoke alarms in your house will start ringing
or buzzing or making a sound so that you will be alerted
that there is a problem.
What saved me because it was a real close call.
It shouldn't have taken more than than a couple of seconds
later I would have been dead.
The smoke was enormous and the heat.
And if I hadn't heard the sound of the breaking glass,
I probably would have died in my sleep.
But I woke up.
What saved me is probably the training that I had in the
past because of my profession.
But even even though with that training it was a difficult one.
I have two advices. That's one.
Don't charge your battery in your house and don't charge it
when you're when you're going to sleep.
I think it's a, it's a precaution
Don't do that.
And secondly, put smoke alarms in your house and make sure
that these alarms are in connection with each other so that
if one goes off, all the rest goes off,
and that you even if you are ten meters away on another
floor, that you will hear it,
that you will be saved by the bell,
by the alert.
I’m okay. This is some time ago now.
Every time when you hear that someone else has not survived
the fire in the house, it makes you think that what
happened to me, that I was extremely lucky.
It makes you also think about the advice that should go out
with a lot of pressure to the people,
like put these smoke alarms in the house.